A Guide to the John D. Clark Papers, 1923-1988
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
John D. Clark Papers, 1923-1988,
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1988-058
4.4 cu. ft. 3 boxes; 1 folder
This collection contains both the professional and personal papers of John D. Clark.
Clark, John D.
Administrative Informatino
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The John D. Clark Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1988.
Biogragraphical Note
John Drury Clark was born August 15, 1907, in Fairbanks, Alaska, to John Albert Clark and Jeanette Ruth Drury. Clark graduated from Fairbanks High School on May 27, 1925. Clark attended the University of Alaska and California Institute of Technology from 1927-1930. He graduated with a B.S. in Physical Chemistry. Clark later received a Master of Science Degree from the University of Wisconsin (1932), and his PhD from Stanford University(1934).
In the early 1930's, Clark worked with General Electric. By 1949, Clark worked with the Naval Air Rocket Program where he had a job until he retired in 1970. Specifically, Clark was the chief chemist at the Naval Air Rocket Test Station and its successor department. He worked in the Liquid Propulsion Laboratory at the Picatinny Arsenal in Dover, New Jersey. Under Clark's direction, a new family of storable high-energy liquid propellants later used in the Apollo program was developed by Navy civilian scientists in 1959.
Clark was married twice, first to soprano singer Mildred Baldwin in 1943. Later he married Inga Pratt, widower of Fletcher Pratt, in 1962. John D. Clark died July, 1988 at age 80 in New Jersey.
Published works:
"A new periodic chart,"Journal of Chemical Education (1933).
"Minus Planet," published in Astounding Stories (Apr 1937). Available in Spec Sci Fi PN6120.95.S33 A88.
"Space Blister," published in Astounding Stories (Aug 1937). Available in Spec Sci Fi PN6120.95.S33 A88.
"A Probable Outline of Conan's Career," with P. Schuyler Miller, published in The Hyborian Age (1938).
"A Modern Periodic Chart of Chemical Elements," Science (1950).
"The Silicone World," published in Startling Stories (December 1952). Available in Spec Sci Fi PS648.S3 S72.
"Introduction" to The Petrified Planet (1952).
"An Informal Biography of Conan the Cimmerian," with P. Schuyler Miller, published in The Coming of Conan (1953).
"An Informal Biography of Conan the Cimmerian," with P. Schuyler Miller and L. Sprague de Camp, published in Amra, vol. 2, no. 4, (1959).
"Science Fact: Dimensions, Anyone?" published in Analog Science Fiction - Science Fact, (November 1966). Available in Spec Sci Fi PN6120.95.S33 A88.
Ignition! An Informal History of Liquid Rocket Propellants, Rutgers University Press (1972). Available in Newman Library TL785 C53.
Resources:
John D. Clark. Ancestry Online Family Trees.
Scope and Content
The collection includes Personal (Series I) and Professional Papers (Series II) of chemist and science fiction writer John D. Clark, dating from 1923-1988. Series I: Personal Papers includes various awards and certificates, photographs, diaries from 1924-1984, student papers, articles written by his father, and correspondence from his mother. There is an additional autobiographical manuscript in in Series II written by John A. Clark called "Reminiscences."
Series II: Professional Papers contains correspondence between colleagues and contemporaries, reports, and Clark's science fiction and non-fiction writing. This includes a manuscript of Ignition!, articles on and by John D. Clark, and various shorter pieces of work. It also contains photographs and a large "proclamation" saluting Clark's work, signed by various colleagues.
Arrangement
This collection in arranged in two series over three boxes. Series I is dedicated to personal papers which are divided into subseries by: A. Biographical Information, B. Diaries, C. Student Work, and D. Papers by John A. Clark and Jeanette Clark. Each subseries is ordered chronologically. If files share a date of origin or are not dated, the files are then organized alphabetically.
Series II contains the professional papers. Series II is divided into sub-series by: A. Correspondence, B. Photographs, C. Administrative Documents, and D. Writing and Related Papers. Correspondence is organized alphabetically by last name. Photographs and Administrative Documents are ordered chronologically.
Sub-series D: Writing and Related Papers, under Series II, is further divided in sub-subseries by manuscript, author, and genre. The sub-subseries are "Non-Fiction on Space," "Reminiscences(John A. Clark)," "Ignition!," "Institute on Man and Science," "Science Fiction Writing," and "Articles by or related to John D. Clark". With the exception of "Reminiscences" and "Ignition!," each sub-subseries is ordered first chronologically and then alphabetically if multiple files share a date or are undated. "Ignition!" and "Reminiscences" are ordered by chapter.
Index Terms
Persons:
Clark, Jeanette; Clark, John A; Clark, John D.
Subjects:
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Science and Technology
Occupations:
Chemists
Genre and Form Terms:
Science Fiction
Contents List
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Subseries A: Biographical Information, 1907-1980
    - JDC- Certificates, Degrees, societies, Awards, etc., 1907-1969 (Box-folder 1-1)
    - California Institute of Technology - Golden Anniversary (Class of 1930), 1980 (Box-folder 1-2)
    - American Rocket Society--Membership Certificate, 1961 (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Resumes, Personal History, Statements, 1948-1960 (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Retirement Documents, 1970 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Subseries B: Photographs, 1900-1986
    - Family Photographs, 1900-1920 (Box-folder 1-6)
    - Portraits and Personal Photographs, 1927-1949 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - Portraits and Personal Photographs, 1970-1986 (Box-folder 1-8)
    - Negative Photographs, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Subseries C: Diaries, 1924-1984
    - Diaries 1-3, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 1-10)
    - Diaries 4-6, 1924-1926 (Box-folder 1-11)
    - Diaries 7-9, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 1-12)
    - Diaries 10-12, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 1-13)
    - Diaries 13-15, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 1-14)
    - Diaries 16-18, 1932-1936 (Box-folder 1-15)
    - Diaries 19-21, 1936-1942 (Box-folder 1-16)
    - Diaries 22-24, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 1-17)
    - Diaries 25-27, 1947-1953 (Box-folder 1-18)
    - Diaries 28-30 (missing 30), 1953-1957 (Box-folder 1-19)
    - Diaries 31-33, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 1-20)
    - Diaries 34-36, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 1-21)
    - Diaries 37-39, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 1-22)
    - Diaries 40-42, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 1-23)
    - Diaries 43-45, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 1-24)
    - Diaries 46-47, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Subseries D: Student Work, c. 1928-29
    - Student Papers--Stanford University, C.A. 1928 (Box-folder 1-26)
    - Student Papers--Stanford University, C.A.1929 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Subseries E: John A. and Jeanette Drury Clark Papers, 1906-1984, n.d.
    - John A. Clark--Letter of Introduction fo JDC, n.d. (Box-folder 1-28)
    - John A. Clark--University Of Alaska Papers, 1986 (Box-folder 1-29)
    - Contract RE: Literary Rights to John A. Clark Memoirs, 1937 (Box-folder 1-30)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence RE: John A. Clark Memoirs,n.d. 1950 (Box-folder 1-31)
    - John A. Clark Memoirs--Outline, n.d. (Box-folder 1-32)
    - John A. Clark--Untitled Letters, n.d. (Box-folder 1-33)
    - John A. Clark --"Indoor Sports," n.d. (Box-folder 1-34)
    - Clark, Jeannette Drury--Letter (Photocopy), 1906 (Box-folder 1-35)
    - John A Clark--Will, Obituary, etc., 1931 (Box-folder 1-36)
- Series II: Professional Papers
  - Subseries A: Correspondence, 1931-1986
    - General Correspondence, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 1-37)
    - General Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 1-38)
    - General Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 1-39)
    - General Correspondence, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 1-40)
    - Ament, W.S.--Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 1-41)
    - Asimov, Isaac--Correspondence, 1961-1984 (Box-folder 1-42)
    - Bova, Ben--Correspondence, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 1-43)
    - Campbell, John W.--Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 1-44)
    - Ciardi, John--Correspondence, n.d. (Box-folder 1-45)
    - DeCamp, Sprague--Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 1-46)
    - Dees, K.W.--Correspondence, 1964 (Box-folder 1-47)
    - Dees, K.W.--Correspondence, 1965 (Box-folder 1-48)
    - Dees K.W.--Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1-49)
    - Dees, K.W.--Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 1-50)
    - Dees, Clark--Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2-1)
    - Depalma, Bruce--Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 2-2)
    - Dunn, Bruce P. --Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 2-3)
    - Ferman, Edward L.--Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 2-4)
    - Frelinghuysen, Peter--Correspondence, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 2-5)
    - Halvorsen, Hal--Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 2-6)
    - Hood, G. Raymond--Correspondence, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 2-7)
    - Jomes, Phyllis--Correspondence,CA. 1970-76 (Box-folder 2-8)
    - Knight, Damon--Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 2-9)
    - Lear, John--Correspondence, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 2-10)
    - Mendenhall, Stephen--Correspondence, 1979 (Box-folder 2-11)
    - Nogales, Rafel De--Correspondence, 1931 (Box-folder 2-12)
    - Okun, Nathan--Correspondence, CA.1979-81 (Box-folder 2-13)
    - Prendergast, Maurice--Correspondence, 1943-1949 (Box-folder 2-14)
    - Snow, Jack--Letter, 1945 (Box-folder 2-15)
    - Sugioka, Ichird--Correspondence, CA. 1978-82 (Box-folder 2-16)
    - Young, William E.--Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Subseries B: Photographs, 1935-1960
    - Pratt, Fletcher and Inga--Photographs, CA. 1935-56 (Box-folder 2-18)
    - Pratt, Fletcher and Inga--Photographs, CA. 1935-56 (Box-folder 2-19)
    - Pratt, Fletcher--Naval War Game Photographs, CA.1940 (Box-folder 2-20)
    - NARTS--LRPC Period--Photographs, CA. 1955-60 (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Subseries C: Reports, Notes, and Research Materials, 1930-1980
    - Letters of Commendation, 1936-1970 (Box-folder 2-22)
    - "A New Periodic Chart" (JDC), 1933 (Box-folder 2-23)
    - "Dielectric Properties"--Various Articles by John D. Clark and others, 1933-1935 (Box-folder 2-24)
    - "The Dumbell Theory of Light" (JDC), 1935 (Box-folder 2-25)
    - "Guide for Technical Report Writing" (JDC), 1950 (Box-folder 2-26)
    - Position Descriptions, CA. 1950-66 (Box-folder 2-27)
    - "Considerations in the Choice of a Rocket Propellent" (JDC), 1951 (Box-folder 2-28)
    - "The Heavy Cruiser" (JDC), 1953 (Box-folder 2-29)
    - "The Corrosivity of Fuming Nitric Acid" (JDC), 1955 (Box-folder 2-30)
    - Periodic Table of Isotopes, CA.1955 (Box-folder 2-31)
    - Patent Data, CA. 1956-64 (Box-folder 2-32)
    - "Rocket Juice" (JDC), CA. 1955 (Box-folder 2-33)
    - "What Makes A high Energy Propellant?" (JDC), CA. 1955 (Box-folder 2-34)
    - "The INQD of ISP Calculations" (JDC), 1958-1961 (Box-folder 2-35)
    - "Dark Horse in The Propellant Race" (JDC), 1958 (Box-folder 2-36)
    - "Comprehensive Survey of the Liquid Propellant Rocket Field," 1960 (Box-folder 2-37)
    - High Energy Liquid Monopropellants--Report, 1960 (Box-folder 2-38)
    - Remarks of Chairman, Session on High Energy Monopropellants, 3rd Monopropellant Conference," CA. 1960 (Box-folder 2-39)
    - "Titrimetric Analysis of Mixtures of Hydrazine and Methyl Hydrazine," 1961 (Box-folder 2-40)
    - Pennsalt Chemicals Corp.--Project 105989 Interim Report, 1961 (Box-folder 2-41)
    - "Titrimetric Analysis of Mixtures of Hydrazine an Methyl Hydrazine" (JDC and Joseph R. Smith), 1961 (Box-folder 2-42)
    - Picatinny Arsenal Reports (JDC), 1962-1969 (Box-folder 2-43)
    - Dimensional Analysis--Miscellaneous Notes, CA. 1965-67 (Box-folder 2-44)
    - Dimensional Analysis--"Dimensions, Anyone"(JDC), CA. 1966 (Box-folder 2-45)
    - Dimensional Analysis--"Dimensions, Anyone?" Correspondence 1966 (Box-folder 2-46)
    - "Oxidizers for Prepackaged Missiles for Ship Board Use" (JDC), CA. 1966-72 (Box-folder 2-47)
    - Reviews of MSS for Rutgers University Press, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 2-48)
    - Dimensional Analysis-- "Towards a Rational System of Physical Units," CA. 1975 (Box-folder 2-49)
    - Commercial Rocketry, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 2-50)
    - U.S. Naval Air Rocket Test Station Reports (JDC), 1951-1954 (Box-folder 2-51)
    - U.S. Naval Air Rocket Test Station Reports (JDC), 1955-1956 (Box-folder 2-52)
    - U.S. Naval Air Rocket Test Station Reports (JDC), 1957-1958 (Box-folder 2-53)
    - Particles--Articles, Notes, etc., CA. 1958 (Box-folder 2-54)
    - Dees, K.W.--Miscellaneous Tables and Notes, CA. 1964-67 (Box-folder 2-55)
    - Cryptography, CA. 1974 (Box-folder 2-56)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Files, CA. 1930-80 (Box-folder 2-57)
  - Subseries D: Writing and Related Papers, 1972-1987, n.d.
    - Sub-subseries 1: Non-Fiction on Space, 1960-1971, n.d.
      - The Huborian Age by Robert E Howard, abridged by JDC--photocopy, n.d. (Box-folder 3-1)
      - MS for a book on Rockets by JDC and John Gordon, CA. 1960 (Box-folder 3-2)
      - "Introduction to the Space Age"(JDC), CA. 1960 (Box-folder 3-3)
      - "How to be a Cosmologist," CA. 1971 (Box-folder 3-4)
    - Sub-subseries 2 :Reminiscences (John A. Clark), n.d.
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 1, n.d. (Box-folder 3-5)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 2, n.d. (Box-folder 3-6)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 3, n.d. (Box-folder 3-7)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 4, n.d. (Box-folder 3-8)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 5, n.d. (Box-folder 3-9)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 6, n.d. (Box-folder 3-10)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 7, n.d. (Box-folder 3-11)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 8, n.d. (Box-folder 3-12)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 9, n.d. (Box-folder 3-13)
      - Reminiscences--Chapter 10, n.d. (Box-folder 3-14)
      - Reminiscences--Appendixes n.d. (Box-folder 3-15)
    - Sub-subseries 3: Ignition!
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch I), n.d. (Box-folder 3-16)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch II), n.d. (Box-folder 3-17)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch III), n.d. (Box-folder 3-18)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch IV), n.d. (Box-folder 3-19)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch V), n.d. (Box-folder 3-20)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch VI), n.d. (Box-folder 3-21)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch VII), n.d. (Box-folder 3-22)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch VIII), n.d. (Box-folder 3-23)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch IX), n.d. (Box-folder 3-24)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch X), n.d. (Box-folder 3-25)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch XI), n.d. (Box-folder 3-26)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch XII), n.d. (Box-folder 3-27)
      - Ignition--Photocopy Transcript(Ch XIII), n.d. (Box-folder 3-28)
      - Ignition ! (Through CH 4)-- Marked: "Extra Copy Unedited," n.d. (Box-folder 3-29)
      - Ignition ! (CH 5-10)-- Marked: "Extra Copy Unedited," n.d. (Box-folder 3-30)
      - Ignition ! (CH 11-END)-- Marked: "Extra Copy Unedited," n.d. (Box-folder 3-31)
      - Ignition--Corrections and Correspondence, n.CA. 1970-72 (Box-folder 3-32)
      - Ignition!--Reviews, CA. 1972-73 (Box-folder 3-33)
    - Sub-subseries 4:Institute on Man and Science, 1950-1984
      - Bread Loaf Conferences, 1950-1972 (Box-folder 3-34)
      - Institute On Man and Science:"A Week with Isaac Asimov," 1975 (Box-folder 3-35)
      - Institute On Man and Science:"A Community in Space," 1976 (Box-folder 3-36)
      - Institute On Man and Science:"Predicting the Future" and "The Future of Education," 1977 (Box-folder 3-37)
      - Institute On Man and Science:"The Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence," 1979 (Box-folder 3-38)
      - Institute On Man and Science:"Treaties For Space," 1981 (Box-folder 3-39)
      - Institute On Man and Science:"Braving New Worlds: The Craft of Science Fiction," 1982 (Box-folder 3-40)
      - Rensselaerville Institute:"Asimov '83: What if?," 1983 (Box-folder 3-41)
      - Institute On Man and Science:"Asimov 1984," 1984 (Box-folder 3-42)
      - Institute On Man and Science--Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 3-43)
    - Sub-subseries 5: Science Fiction Writing, 1937-1987, n.d.
      - First Fandom, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 3-44)
      - First Fandom, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 3-45)
      - Origional Cartoons, n.d. (Box-folder 3-46)
      - Untitled Manuscripts, n.d. (Box-folder 3-47)
      - "The Adventures of Commodore Goldblatt: The Affair of Diego MaLaria"(JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-48)
      - "The Adventures of Commodore Goldblatt: The Episode of the Poker Game" (JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-49)
      - "Argosy on Venus," n.d. (Box-folder 3-50)
      - "Flash"(JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-51)
      - "La Grand Parade," n.d. (Box-folder 3-52)
      - "Lost Interlude" (JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-53)
      - "Polar Island" (JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-54)
      - "Rendezvous off Deimos" (JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-55)
      - "Ron Hubbard, The Hunter of Baar" (JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-56)
      - "Some Words of Practical Advice," n.d. (Box-folder 3-57)
      - "Viridians Mutabile" (JDC and D. Mark Baldwin), n.d. (Box-folder 3-58)
      - "Weight" (JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-59)
      - "Gomorrah in the Mist" (JDC), 1937 (Box-folder 3-60)
      - Silverman, S.H. Stories, CA. 1947 (Box-folder 3-61)
      - "The Housing of Mad Scientists," CA. 1951 (Box-folder 3-62)
      - "Trap Door Spiders" (JDC), 1975-1987 (Box-folder 3-64)
      - "Twayne Triplets," CA. 1952 (Box-folder 3-63)
    - Sub-subseries 6: Articles by or Relating to John D. Clark, CA. 1938-85, n.d.
      - "Reapportionment Without Pain" (JDC), n.d. (Box-folder 3-65)
      - Pratt, Fletcher--Naval War Games-- Articles, CA. 1938-65 (Box-folder 3-66)
      - Newspaper and Magazine Articles on JDC, 1941-1973 (Box-folder 3-67)
      - Articles by Others, 1951-1968 (Box-folder 3-68)
      - Letters to Editor, 1967-1985 (Box-folder 3-69)
      - Books to Get, CA. 1970-85 (Box-folder 3-70)
      - New York Times, CA. 1982 (Box-folder 3-71)
  - Subseries E: Oversize Materials
    - Joke Proclamation from Colleagues, 1959 (Folder 1)